They really just don't build them like
they used to. The vast majority of new
housing in the US is single-family
homes, and the vast majority of those
start [music] in the same cheap,
compromised way: an at-grade slab
foundation. These are fine, they do the
job, and they're easy, but they could be
better. [music] The main issue is that
concrete is poured on and around all the
utility lines, so if they're in the
wrong spot, and contractors complain
that they're always in the wrong spot,
complicated fixes will become [music]
necessary down the line, potentially
including tearing up the foundation. If
a homeowner wants to renovate, [music]
it's even worse. Moving utility lines
becomes a huge headache. There is a
better alternative, the crawlspace
foundation, leaving room for utilities
and mechanical elements with the added
perk of a layer to keep moisture and
termites away from the home, [music] but
these are more costly to build, so 73%
of the time, American homes start with
that [music] at-grade slab foundation.
Next, builders move on to constructing
the structural skeleton of [music] the
home, and this is where the US is really
unique. It builds with wood. [music]
The US isn't entirely alone in this.
Canada, Australia, Japan, and Scotland,
too, primarily use the material, but on
a global scale, timber-framed homes are
fairly rare. By and large, wealthier
countries tend to build with brick and
concrete, [music]
while perceiving wood as cheap. And
they're right. Wood is cheap, especially
[music]
in the US. A standard 8-ft 2x4 currently
costs just $4, and unlike other building
materials, [music] you don't need that
many of them to build a house.
Carpenters construct each section of
wall on the ground, spacing planks
either 16 or 24 inches apart. This
spacing is industry standard in the US,
allowing for compatibility with other
building materials down the line.
Occasional horizontal support is placed,
and additional wood is used to reinforce
the openings for windows and doors,
[music]
but unlike the concrete or brick,
there's a whole lot of dead space left
in these walls. This drives down
material cost, but equally importantly,
the process of framing drives down labor
costs. It's just so much quicker than,
say, [music] bricklaying. That's the
predominant style of home construction
in England, for example, and it leads to
[music] a stark difference in
construction cost.
In the US, there's no certification or
formal experience [music] needed to work
as a framer. People will quite literally
play a hand in building a house on their
first day on the job. Well, of course,
there are hierarchies within crews and
more experienced individuals are
assigned to more [music] skill-dependent
tasks, American framers learn by doing.
In England, [music]
the equivalent job is done by
bricklayers who, as with most trades in
the country, practically must go through
a 2-year structured apprenticeship
combining classroom instruction with
[music] on-site experience to gain a
full-time job. This means that
bricklaying tends to be a lifelong
career in England. While American
framing crews are typically led by
career carpenters, [music]
much of each crew is often made up of
relatively entry-level laborers since
many [music] of the tasks in framing can
be done by those without a tremendous
amount of experience. Wages actually
tend to average about the same between
English bricklayers [music] and American
framers, about $28 an hour, but that
means labor is effectively more
expensive in [music] the UK since
average income is about a quarter lower.
Bricklaying also takes much more labor.
While it depends how large the crew is,
framing an American house is often done
in just 1 to 2 weeks, whereas the
equivalent bricklaying process in
England [music] lasts 1 to 2 months. Add
on the higher material costs and the
American home framing process is much,
much cheaper than the English
equivalent.
England actually used to build most of
its homes with wood, but towards the end
of the Middle Ages, it just ran [music]
out of it. Region by region, between
about 1200 and 1600, builders were
pushed towards brick as it became more
and more difficult to find high-quality
timber. Today, the UK has some farmed
forestry land, particularly in Scotland,
but the vast majority of its wood comes
from Scandinavia, driving up costs. The
same 2 by 4 that sells for an average of
$4 in the US goes [music] for about $6
in the UK. Once you add that 50% cost
increase to the entire [music] frame,
the cost competitiveness of wood versus
brick is far weaker in the UK. But,
similar environmental factors have
influenced the US home building process,
as well. [music] In the next step of the
process, the frame needs to be turned
into solid walls, but builders [music]
don't use solid wood for this. Similar
to the UK, the US logged primarily
natural forests for much [music] of its
250 years of expansion, but by the
1950s, the economics shifted. The
easy-to-access old-growth trees were
mostly gone, so the logging industry
shifted to managed farmed [music]
forests. Trees are now predominantly
planted on privately owned land and cut
down 30 or so years later. But, these
farmed trees are much smaller than those
of yesteryear. [music]
They're still thick enough that the
center can be cut into long straight
2x4s, but much of the outer portion of
the log is sliced into thin cuts of wood
that are then mixed with a resin glue
and pressed into flat boards, what are
known as OSB [music] boards. Now, not
only are these far cheaper than solid
wood, since they use the less valuable
parts of the tree, but they're also
better suited for construction, since
they have less potential for weak
points. They have [music] consistent
strength throughout. While these boards
might not be the most aesthetic, they'll
never be seen once the house is done, so
they're the best suited option for the
exterior sheathing. More engineered wood
is used in the next step in the process,
as well, as carpenters start on the
second story. The structural part of
floors is typically built with I-joists,
which are prefabricated, standardized,
widely available products selling for
[music] $40 to $60 that can each hold
thousands of pounds of weight. It's the
same story with the roof, which these
days is often built using prefabricated,
factory-built trusses. Also quite cheap,
often under $100, depending on width.
Building the roof used to be one of the
most time-consuming and skill-dependent
parts of framing a house. Rafters would
have to be precisely cut to meet at a
consistent angle, all while carpenters
dangled one or two stories above the
ground. Roof trusses do that complicated
part on a mass manufacturing [music]
line at a factory, making framing the
roof as simple as fastening down each
truss and affixing some [music] OSB
boards on top. There are some downsides.
They use up space that would otherwise
act as usable attic. They burn faster in
a fire. They're almost impossible to
modify. But, the upsides have won out in
the marketplace [music] and they're now
fairly standard in lower cost homes.
Similar compromises have been made on
the industry standard method to seal the
roof as well. After a protective
synthetic underlayment is laid out,
which some would argue is worse than the
traditional felt equivalent, American
roofers typically install large sheets
of shingles. These can be installed
remarkably fast by just positioning them
in place and firing off a nail gun. A
single experienced individual can often
install 7 or 800 square feet of shingles
in a day, meaning a roofing crew
comprised of multiple workers often
completes the whole job in a day. Once
again comparing that to England, while
these sheets of shingles are an option
there, the default material of choice
for low-cost roofing is concrete tiles.
These are also mass-manufactured, but
while the American three-tab shingles
cost about a dollar and a half per
square foot, these go for more like two
and a quarter. They're also far [music]
more time-consuming to install, meaning
all in, an English roof costs about
double that of an American one. The
trade-off, of course, is durability. An
American roof must be replaced about
once every 15 to 30 years, depending on
the harshness of the local climate. In
England, [music] that process typically
doesn't happen for 50 years, meaning in
the lifespan of a home, it ends up
similarly priced and more [music]
convenient. The American system
optimizes for low upfront cost at the
expense of long-term durability.
Next, workers install the aesthetic
exterior of the house, typically vinyl
siding for low-cost builds. This style
of siding is incredibly easy to install.
For the most part, it just snaps in
place, [music] then all that's needed is
a hammer and nails to affix it to the
wall. Like the roof, an average
installation can be done by a small crew
in just a day.
Vinyl siding comes with some real
compromises. It can crack in the cold,
melt in magnified sunlight, fade in
color through time, leak water. [music]
It's not a great material, but it's
super cheap to buy and install, so it's
the option of choice for cheap builds in
the US. But perhaps the greatest
efficiency magic of the US home building
process happens [music] next as
electricians and plumbers come in and
install its mechanical backbone. With
all the open space between the studs in
each wall, the process of installing the
wires, pipes, and [music] ducts for
electrical, plumbing, and HVAC systems
is incredibly simple. It's in part for
this reason in fact that American houses
come standard issue with what's
considered a massive luxury in the UK,
[music]
air conditioning. Now, of course much of
the reason the UK lacks air conditioning
is that its climate rarely calls for it,
but that's far from the whole story.
>> [music]
>> London and Seattle's summer highs are
near identical, yet their AC adoption is
not. In London just about 5% of homes
have it, whereas in Seattle that portion
is over 50%. American homes default to
ducts for [music] heating in part
because they're fairly simple to install
through the open timber frames. With
ducts already there, adding an AC
condenser to the system is a rather
trivial additional expense that many
consider justified even if it only be
put to use during the occasional summer
heat wave. English homes tend to heat
using radiators in part due to the
easier installation of the necessary
pipes through brick walls, so installing
AC is a whole separate process typically
requiring the installation of unsightly
and noisy ductless units [music] in each
large room. Once all the mechanicals are
in, insulation goes next, which is also
a fairly straightforward process thanks
to pre-cut rolls sized for the standard
[music] 16 or 24-in spacing between
studs. Finally, interior walls are
sealed by installing drywall, an
incredibly straightforward process
entailing just simply screwing it into
the stud. Then of course there are all
the aesthetic elements, paint, [music]
floors, cabinets, finishes, and more,
but by this point the house is
structurally done. A typical lower end
home in the US, particularly in a
development, will get to this point
within two [music] months. Meanwhile in
England, two months in, it's not
uncommon for brick laying to still be
going on.
Bricks do last longer, though. So do
concrete tile roofs, radiator heating,
and just about every element of the
average English home. They're built
stronger, they last longer, they're more
efficient. The average Englishman has
every reason to be pompous about the
build quality of their home, if they can
afford one.
Relative to income, housing is
meaningfully more expensive in [music]
the UK than the US. Their average house
costs about 6.5 times average annual
income, whereas [music] it's about five
times more in the US. The American style
of home building is extremely
cost-efficient, and while a relative
lack of durability does drive up
long-term maintenance costs, the vast
majority of American homes are perfectly
suited for their purpose and don't have
any [music] existential issues in their
construction. But with the highly
efficient, comparatively lower-skilled
process of American home building allows
for, however, is the potential of
sloppier construction. Considering the
steps in the process are designed to
rely less on costlier, highly skilled
labor, [music]
lower-skilled labor can build an
American home. That doesn't mean that
most American homes are built by
lower-skilled labor, but with a lack of
a strong, nationwide system of
certification of builders,
>> [music]
>> there is the potential for sloppy
construction in a way that there's less
of in the UK. By and large, though,
American homes are not necessarily worse
than their international [music]
equivalents when you consider their
price. They just optimize for low
upfront construction costs rather than
low long-term maintenance [music] and
energy costs. If one were to pick the
cardinal sin of the American home
building system, it's not that it relies
on timber or other cheaper building
materials, but it's that the US doesn't
take advantage of its advantage. Each
American has, on average, more than
double the living space of the average
Brit, [music] about 800 square feet
versus just 390.
The way America builds homes is
extraordinarily [music]
efficient, but then it pours those
efficiencies into size. While space is
nice, it's a luxury, while housing is a
necessity. And even [music] if the US's
housing crisis is not as bad as the
UK's, it's still a crisis, particularly
in the most in-demand regions and for
young people. While construction cost is
only one of a multitude of factors
influencing housing cost,
>> [music]
>> the US could have more affordable
housing, and particularly more
affordable single-family homes, if it
just built smaller.
American housing ignores the needs of
those in greatest need while serving the
middle class most. It may be
comparatively flimsy. It may break down
sooner than it needs to, but that
downside is a trade-off for an upside
many Americans value. [music]
It's mass-market luxury. It's quantity
over quality. It's quintessentially
American, for better or worse.
Quintessentially American, for better or
worse, would also be an excellent
description of this season of Jetlag the
Game, State Shaped Scramble. The
season's already a good few episodes in,
and it's a really fun one because we
brought Amy, of HAI and Abolish
Everything fame, into compete alongside
me all the way across the US. We're
really proud of this season, and
honestly, we're really proud of every
season because Jetlag just takes a lot
of effort from a big team to make
happen. If you'd like to catch up, or if
you'd like to get ahead, I recommend
giving it a watch on its home platform,
Nebula. A streaming service built out by
us creators to allow us to showcase some
of our best, most creative work, and
provide you all with more of the content
that brings you to this channel and all
of our channels to begin with. Because
Jetlag is a Nebula original, the entire
library, every episode of every season,
lives on the platform for you to fly
through without any ads. And because
it's a Nebula original, if you want to
get a week ahead on the episodes, you
can do so on Nebula. And access to
Jetlag is really just only the tip of
the content iceberg. It's where our
team's bigger-budget documentary
projects live. It's where our comedy
debate show lives. And it's also where a
whole host of your favorite creators are
posting some of their most innovative
stuff. If travel is your thing, Mike
Downey series Downey Express just
recently posted its finale episode of
season 3 going Bangkok to Bali. If
transport is your thing, get on board
with Jason from Not Just Bikes with his
limited series exploring some of the
most interesting European transit
systems one by one. If you're looking
for really anything from your favorite
creators that pushes their creative
boundaries, or perhaps it's just too
close to potentially budding up against
restrictive content guidelines, or just
not optimized for all important
virality, Nebula is the place to find
it. It's a platform we've all worked
really hard to build out. It's one that
just keeps getting better and deeper as
we all keep adding content. And if you
want to give it a try, it's pretty darn
cheap. Follow my link nebula.tv/wendover
and you'll get 50% off an annual
subscription. That makes it only $30 for
a year, or $2.50 a month. If you want to
give it a shot, we couldn't be more
appreciative. So, thanks.